大家好，我是Tim Dodd，欢迎观看本期的《每日宇航员》
Hi it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut
太空叉的猎鹰九号火箭——世界上第一个可复用火箭
SpaceX's Falcon 9 rocket, the world's first reusable rocket
停一下！
Wait!
不对吧
No it's not
还记得航天飞机吗？
Do you remember the Space Shuttle?
航天飞机的轨道器和固体火箭助推器都是可复用的不是吗？
It had those Solid Rocket Boosters, and the Orbiter which were both reusable weren't they?
今天我们就来谈谈，为啥航天飞机就没法实现真正意义的复用
Well today we're going to talk about why the Space Shuttle failed to actually be reusable
也引入一个更准确的表述，可翻新的
and wound up being described with a more accurate word, refurbishable
到处都能见到有人拿航天飞机的毛病
People often cite the shortcomings of the Space Shuttle
去把太空叉的猎鹰九号批判一番
and are quick to point it to SpaceX's claims of the Falcon 9 booster being reusable
所以今天我们来看看
So today we're going to look at what it takes to get the Space Shuttle operational between flights
猎鹰九号究竟是凭借着什么才能每次发射进退自如
what it takes to get a Falcon 9 operational between flights
为啥太空叉的一级火箭能比太空飞机高到不知哪里去
and why SpaceX's first stage booster take much less of a beating than the Space Shuttle did
顺便还要回顾一下
We'll also do a quick reminder
太空叉为了让Block 5的一级能达成目标
of what technologies SpaceX added to their Block 5 booster
往上面又加了什么新技术
to hopefully achieve their goal of making a rapidly reusable rocket
以至于就算没做什么大修，它也能被射个10次
that can truly be reused 10 times before needing any kind of serious refurbishment
走你！
Let's get started!
- 3, 2, 1, 0
- Three, two, one, zero
起飞！
and lift off
这是人类的一小步
- That's one small step for man
毫无疑问，可复用是如今航天界最热的词
- Reusable is definitely the hottest buzz word in the new space industry
如果你不知道为什么这概念能引领时代
If you don't know why a vehicle being reusable is such a massive game changer
我建议你看看我过往视频叫《为啥重型猎鹰很重要》
may I suggest checking out my video Why does Falcon Heavy matter
深入浅出解释可复用性的重要性
to help get a good perspective on why reusability matters
长话短说就是发挥空间太小
the margins to get stuff to space are so thin
把那么多东西射上天需要巨大的火箭
it takes a massive rocket to put anything substantial up there
因此基本没有多余的重量让你安装回收装置了
So unfortunately there's just too little margins left over to add additional hardware to make a rocket reusable
这就会让航天变得超级、无比、极其昂贵
This makes spaceflight extremely, extremely expensive
以至于把成本降到每千克”仅1000美金“都只能是期望
As in, so expensive we're hoping to someday see costs come down to "just a $1000" per kilogram!
想象一下你在地球上遇到了这种水平的运费
Yeah, imagine those shipping costs down here on Earth
喂，你那订个伊兰特的轮胎要多少钱啊？
Hi there, I'm calling to get a quote for some new tires for my 2011 Hyundai Elantra
废话当然是GT款
Yes of course it's the GT model
我在地上漂移摩擦和地面保持零距离
I did some really cool drifting and so that's why the tires are bad
到底要多少钱啊？
How much would the new tires be?
才400刀？
Oh $400?
邮费多少啊？
How much for shipping?
三万六？？？
$36000!
但是相比先前往天上射东西的价格，这跟包邮没两样
And that would actually be a steal compared to the historically astronomical prices of getting space hardware into space
就算是历史最低价，也得要3000刀左右才能运个1千克
Even the cheapest dollar to kilogram ratio is around the $3000 per kilogram mark
就这还完全是靠猎鹰九号和重型猎鹰才压下来的价位
thanks to the Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy
只能说还好火箭送快递目前还不是主流了
It's a good thing rocket delivery isn't the standard here on Earth
这就能解释为啥会需要可复用了
So here's where reusability comes in
毫无疑问！
It's honestly fundamental! Of course!
光是个引擎就几百上千万块钱的
Why throw away super expensive multi-million dollar engines
更别说还有箭身和一大堆零件
and a massive fuselage and all that extra stuff
你寻思我这旧火箭不要了？
when you could just reuse it, right?
对不起，我们是穷鬼
I mean duh!
这就是为啥要发明航天飞机了
Well that was the original idea for the Space Shuttle
信不信由你
Believe it or not
NASA早在人类登月之前
NASA was seeking a reusable launch vehicle
就已经想要这么个玩意了
before we even put humans on the moon
研究开始于1968年
The original studies began in 1968
比阿姆斯特朗月球上那个著名的一小一大步
some 10 months before Neil Armstrong
早了差不多十个月
famously took the first steps on the moon
事实上
As a matter of fact
航天飞机最初的飞行员，约翰·杨
one of the first people to fly the Space Shuttle, John Young
接到航天飞机项目获批的消息时，正好在月面上行走
was walking on the moon when he got news of the shuttle
- 时候不错，我跟你说个好消息
- This looks like a good time for some good news here
白宫277票比60票通过了航天预算审批
The House passed the space budget yesterday, 277 to 60
当然也包括航天飞机的预算
which includes the votes for the shuttle
- 流批，太棒了!
- That's wonderful, wonderful
Tony我跟你讲
- Tony, again I'll say it, with that salute
身为美国人真吼哇！
I'm proud to be an American
多好的项目，多好的地点，多好的经历！
I'll tell you, what a program and what a place and what an experience
所言极是
- Yeah, and I'll say it too
我也会这么说
- So am I
我们的国家渴望航天飞机
Country needs that shuttle mighty bad
但事情的结果却与期望恰恰相反
- So with all the excitement leading up to the shuttle
回到50年后的今天
fast forward 50 years to today
人们对航天飞机的态度转向了相反的方向
and the Space Shuttle has kind of a bad taste in our mouths
且不说贵上了天，安全性也得不到保障
It wound up being terribly expensive, pretty dangerous
论成本，它称第二，没人敢称第一，第三差了十万八千里
and actually more expensive than just about any other way to get into space
尽管有些实验只能在航天飞机上操作，所以也不能说毫无意义
although it could do things that no other launch vehicle could do
所以，一堆世界上最高级的大脑设计出来的航天器
So with some of the greatest minds working on the shuttle
咋还是没法按预期那样把成本降下来呢
why did it fail its promise of bringing the cost down?
太空叉是命中注定要复现历史，还是50年来早已天翻地覆？
Is SpaceX doomed to repeat history or has a lot changed in 50 years?
首先，对比一下两者的回收系统
So first, let's look at the recovery methods of each system
这里就能体现出相当多的问题
They're quite different
航天飞机的回收主要依靠降落伞和升力体机身
The Space Shuttle utilized both parachutes and a lifting body to recover hardware
所以我们依次看看回收的都有啥
Let's go in order of what was recovered
首先是固体助推器
so starting with the Solid Rocket Boosters
大概起飞两分钟后被直接抛弃
which were jettisoned around two minutes into flight
助推器大概在4800km/h的速度时从航天器分离
The boosters separate while traveling around 4800 kilometers an hour or 3000 miles an hour
高度大约45公里
at an altitude of around 45 kilometers or 30 miles
之后还会因为速度一直上升到65公里的高度
And due to their velocity they continue to coast upward to their highest point of around 65 kilometers or 40 miles
顺便，这也就是说那些固体助推器
Just a fun note that does means the SRBs never actually make it
从来都没有到过卡门线，也就是说从来都没出过大气层
above the Karman line or the commonly agreed upon boundary of space
记好咯
So keep that in mind
助推器穿过大气层
The boosters fall back through the atmosphere
在4786米的高度，开始放出一连串的降落伞
and start popping a sequence of parachutes at exactly 4786 meters or 15704 feet
先是引导伞，接着是减速伞
Eventually after a pilot chute, and a drogue chute
最后放出三个主伞
the three main parachutes deploy
然后溅落海面，还算是软着陆
and splish splash the booster down relatively softly in the ocean
另一方面的轨道器，就比两个助推器啊，跑得还快
The Orbiter on the other hand is traveling much, much faster
所以这玩意的回收进程，就要火热得多
and its recovery, like all orbital things, is a lot hotter
提前一个小时，就要来个大转身
About one hour before touchdown, the Orbiter turns around
屁股朝前脸向后
and faces away from its direction of travel or prograde
启动轨道机动系统（OMS），降低1%的速度
It fires up its orbital maneuvering system or OMS and slows down 1%
对，你没听错，就是只有1%！
Yep, that's it, only about 1%!
不过这也完全足够
And that's enough to lower its orbit
将飞机的轨道从480公里
from about 480 kilometers or 300 miles
降低到最低点只有45千米的轨道上
down to just 45 kilometers or 28 miles at its lowest point
Crazy个头，玩过KSP都懂
That's crazy
然后呢这个航天飞机还要再转个身
The Orbiter then turns back around
头朝前，保持约40度仰角
so it can reenter at about a 40 degree angle
接下来就是靠大气层的工作了
Now it's time for the atmosphere to do its work
这时候航天飞机还是巡航在这个轨道上
The Orbiter is absolutely cruising at this point
依然保持着大约27000km/h的速度
It's still traveling around 27000 kilometers an hour or 17000 miles an hour
接着，空气分子开始撞击我们的飞机
the Orbiter begins to hit air molecules
产生极大的摩擦力
and starts to build up a ton of friction
也就产生了极大的热量
and therefore a ton of heat
最烫的时候甚至能烧到1650°C！
The Orbiter will reach temperatures of 1650 degrees Celsius or 3000 degrees Fahrenheit!
烫烫烫
Ouch!
但还好航天飞机真的很耐操，有4套不同的隔热系统
But luckily, the Orbiter is covered with four different types of thermal protection
一是机翼前缘强化碳-碳复合材料
It has reinforced carbon-carbon on the leading edges
二是机腹与前部安装的共计24177到31088块不等的绝热瓦
then there were between 24177 and 31088 tiles, depending on the Orbiter
这个数字取决于机型
on the underside and front of the vehicle
三是上舱门、上翼面与机身会用白色Nomex绝热毯覆盖
then there is white Nomex blankets on the upper payload bay doors, the upper wing and fuselage
最后是一些同为白色的表面绝热瓦用于隔绝相对较低的温度
and a few white surface tiles for low temperature areas as well
到着陆前最后12分钟，航天飞机表面会被炽热的电离气体覆盖
For 12 minutes, the shuttle had so much hot ionized gases
这就导致完全无法与外界通信，也就是所谓的黑障
surrounding the vehicle, it caused a full radio blackout
在空气摩擦的作用下
Eventually, after several minutes of atmospheric drag
配合精妙计算得出的S型飞行轨迹
and some computer guided S-turns
航天飞机靠这样才能减到比较正常的速度
the shuttle bleeds off a lot of its velocity
同时，一旦高度降低到40千米以下
Once it's about 40 kilometers or 25 miles downrange
飞机会调整为20度俯角
the commander drops the nose to minus 20 degrees
没概念的话，这是正常客机的近7倍
that's almost seven times steeper than a commercial airliner
而速度则快了20倍！
and it's still traveling 20 times faster
不过最后落地的姿势倒是没太大区别，速度只稍微快了一点点
Finally the shuttle lands like a traditional jetliner only a little quicker
到了350km/h，而跑道也足足有4.5千米长
touching down at 350 kilometers an hour or 220 miles an hour on a 4.5 kilometer or 2.8 mile long runway
这长度，光是因为地球表面弧度
That runway's actually so long that there's over a one and a half meter or over 5 feet in relative height difference
就已经造成超过1.5米的高度差了！
between the ends of the runway due to the curve of the Earth!
流批吧
That's crazy
欢迎回家!
It's quite the journey! Welcome home, Space Shuttle
让我们再回来看看50年之后猎鹰九号的回收方式
So now, let's do a quick rundown on how a Falcon 9 is recovered
虽然我已经有说过好几次了
I've covered this topic a few times, more in depth
如果还有哪里不懂的话
so if you have any questions remaining
我再次建议你看看我的过往视频《太空叉如何回收猎鹰九号》
check out my video How SpaceX lands the Falcon 9
升空约2分40秒之后，一级关机
At around two minutes and 40 seconds into flight the Falcon 9 shuts down its main engines
也就是经常听到的MECO
called MECO or main engine cut off
继续滑行一小段时间之后
It coasts for a moment
一级会与二级分离
and then the first stage lets go of the second stage for stage separation
这时候就已经达到最大8000km/h的速度
At this point the Falcon 9 is traveling up to 8000 kilometers an hour or almost 5000 miles an hour
与65千米的高度了
at an altitude of 65 kilometers or 40 miles
如果你还记得航天飞机那个固体助推器的话，那速度才到这一半
Quick note, that's about twice as fast as the Space Shuttle's rocket boosters
接着，一级火箭会用其氮助推器做一个翻转动作
The first stage quickly performs a flip maneuver
尾部发动机向前
with its nitrogen thrusters, to point its engines prograde
然后，根据任务情况的不同
Then, depending on the mission
一级可能会点燃其9个发动机中的3个来做
boost back burn
可是万一剩下的燃料不是很够
But there might not be enough margins left over to do the boost back burn
就只好跳过这个步骤，让一级凭借惯性继续向上滑行
In that case it's omitted and the Falcon 9 continues on its ballistic trajectory away from the launch pad and heads towards the drone ship
至于具体采用哪种方式，在每次任务的页面上都有写
that's been precisely placed based on each mission profile
不过不管怎样
But in either case
这个助推器都会向上一直冲到
the booster will coast up to its highest point
高度为100千米的卡门线以上
typically over the Karman line or 100 kilometers or 62 miles
换言之
In other words
至少有那么一瞬间，助推器会冲出大气层之外！
the booster gets to hang out in space for a minute or so!
不知道啥时候我也能去啊
Lucky, I wanna go
等到助推器再入大气层
Around 55 kilometers or 34 miles in altitude
下落到大概海拔55千米高的时候
the Falcon 9 will light up three of its nine Merlin engines
猎鹰九号的3发引擎会重新点火（reentry burn）
as it reenters the atmosphere
以此来降低下落速度
It does this to slow itself down
同时还会形成一个力场
and it actually creates a literal force field around itself
以保证助推器不会在载入过程中烧毁
so it can survive reentry
在完成大约20秒的再入点火之后
After around 20 seconds of reentry burn
助推器能减掉其30%到40%的速度
the booster scrubs off 30 to 40% of its velocity
这样，下落过程中摩擦生的热就不会再对机身构成任何威胁了
which is enough to withstand the remaining heat
再往后，原本稀薄的大气变得越来越浓厚
as the atmosphere gets thicker and thicker
助推器将借此减掉剩下那60%到70%的速度
The atmosphere will then take off another 60 to 70% of the remaining velocity
最后，到只剩下约1000km/h的时候
until the booster is only traveling about 1000 kilometers an hour or 620 miles an hour
火箭会点燃1或者3个Merlin发动机, 进行最终的着陆点火
Then it lights up one or three of its Merlin engines to perform the final landing burn
这一步需要非常精准的时间控制
which it needs to time perfectly
因为就算只开一个发动机，还保持着最小的推力
Even with just one of the nine engines running at its minimum throttle
这也远比火箭本身重力高太多了
the booster still has too much thrust to hover
结果就是，如果点火太早
So if the vehicle stops before it hits the ground
火箭就会再一次飞走
it'll actually start going back up
那还回收个毛线
Yeah, that's not good
这个精确操控时间的机制
This needs to be perfectly timed
被叫做hover-slam或者suicide burn
in a maneuver called the hover-slam or suicide burn
下面的步骤你们也知道，放腿，然后轻轻触地……
Then the landing legs deploy and the Falcon 9 softly touches down
虽然我们都有不顺利的时候
Well, hopefully
这时候就有人会问了，为啥太空叉就不能学学航天飞机的助推器
So before we move on, let's really quick remind you why the Falcon 9 doesn't use parachutes?
多少用一下降落伞啊？
like the Space Shuttle SRBs did
不用当然有不用的理由
Well there's a few reasons
我已经做了好几个相关的视频
and I'm just gonna breeze through these
所以这里就简单罗列一下
since I've done many videos about this
但将来有机会的话
and I probably still need to do
可能还会有更深入地讲解
a more dedicated and updated video about it
Everyday Astronaut理论课堂之
So here's Everyday Astronaut's top seven reasons
猎鹰九号不用降落伞回收的七大理由！
why SpaceX doesn't use parachutes to land the Falcon 9!
首先，人家并不是没用过
One: SpaceX tried to use parachutes
最初两次回收任务就是用的降落伞
on the first two Falcon 9 missions to recover the booster
但是你想想，这玩意可是有航天飞机助推器两倍的速度
Unfortunately, the booster is going about twice as fast as the SRBs
降落伞哪那么简单就承受得了呢
and the parachutes couldn't survive the extra forces
第二，既然火箭本身已经有发动机了
Two: The rocket already has engines capable of slowing down
干嘛放着不用啊？
why not use them?
你见过哪个直升机还需要降落伞来降落的么？
Does a helicopter need a parachute to land?
因为直升机有螺旋桨有发动机啊！
No it has an engine and a propeller already!
第三，太空叉的目标可是去火星啊
Three: You can't land a large rocket
就算降落伞成熟了
on Mars or the moon with a parachute
到了火星到了月球也完全没用
the atmosphere is too thin or nonexistent
不如选个比较通用的方案
So you'd better start practicing propulsive landings now
直接精通，一步到位
and get good at 'em!
第四，一个比较关键的问题是，猎鹰九号最高点会冲到大气层之外
Four: The rocket needs to slow down
以这个速度再入大气层的话，本身就是一个问题
before it hits the atmosphere to survive reentry anyway
因此必须在再入之前就开始减速
Remember that whole reentry burn thing?
而降落伞在大气层之外可没啥效果
Yeah, a parachute can't work very well before it's in the atmosphere
可以说直接用火箭发动机减速是唯一可行的途径了
so rocket engines are the only way to go
第五，降落伞和其附带的一系列系统
Five: Parachutes and the supporting system
会必然地使箭身更长
that would allow the fuselage
也不可避免得增加了死重
to get stretched and not just compressed
并不是更经济的方案
would just add otherwise dead weight
第六，虽然降落伞也不是不能控制
Six: Parachutes, although steerable
但相比柵格翼、低温气体推进器或者万向发动机支撑架
are not nearly as precise as grid fins
那可完全不是一回事
cold gas thrusters and an engine gimbal
看看近期太空叉回收整流罩的情况
SpaceX is finding this out the hard way
你就知道降落伞有多糟糕了
as they tried to catch their fairings under steerable parafoils
最后一点，火箭这玩意不防水
Seven: Splashing down is bad mkay
液体火箭发动机泡盐水，你是要煲汤啊?
Salt water and precise liquid rocket engine don't mix very well
可以说，这是个非常重要的改良
So that's actually a great place to transition
到此，我们已经讨论了
Okay, so now that we recovered
航天飞机的回收部件
the reusable parts of the Space Shuttle
以及猎鹰九号的一级
and the first stage of the Falcon 9
接下来，它们需要怎样的工序才能再次发射呢？
what did they do to prepare them for reflight?
先说说航天飞机
Let's start with the Space Shuttle
要把这家伙重新推上发射架
What did it take to get one back to the launch pad?
第一件事是把掉水里的助推器捞上来
After splashdown, the boosters were sealed up
先由潜水员把助推器的菊花塞上
by scuba divers with a giant plug
然后排空里面的水
where they drained the water
这样（水平漂浮的助推器）才能用拖船拖回肯尼迪航天中心
so it could be towed back to Kennedy Space Center
回收一个助推器需要18人才能完成
Each booster required a crew of 18 for ocean recovery
所以每个航天飞机带两个助推器
The Space Shuttle obviously had two boosters
光是运回家就得36人了
so that's 36 people on booster recovery
然后助推器会被拆开
Then the boosters are disassembled
送往犹他州的普瑞蒙特瑞
and sent out to Promontory, Utah
进行清理、重喷漆
to be cleaned, paint stripped, repainted
详细检查与重新状态固体推进剂
inspected and reloaded with solid propellant
然后重新运回肯尼迪航天中心
Then they go back to Kennedy Space Center
在“美国装配与翻新站“进行组装
for assembly at the United Space Alliance Assembly and Refurbishment Facility
真是个贴切的名字
I like the name of that place
火箭的四段
The four segments in each booster
都会被换上新的点火器
are then mated to a new igniter
前段、头锥、尾裙部、锥台等乱七八糟的东西
forward segment, nose cap, aft skirt and frustum, whatever that is
基本上，真正“复用”的也就是外壳了
So basically just the casing was actually truly reused
所以称之为翻新肯定来的更加准确
I definitely think refurbished is the right word here
把一个东西皮扒下来只剩骨头
considering they stripped it down to the bare metal each time
然后再拿到一个翻新厂里去处理
and taken to a place called the Refurbishment Facility
这完全不是可复用吧！
Okay, so the boosters aren't at all what I'd call reusable
再来看看轨道器
but how about the Orbiter?
助推器的翻新工程相比这玩意的可就是小巫见大巫了
What's it take to actually get that thing reflying?
降落之后
After touching down
会派出150位高级技工
a highly trained crew of 150 people
以及25辆高度定制的车辆
and 25 specially designed vehicles
毕竟航天飞机这会儿没有动力开到停机坪
head out to intercept the vehicle
首先排除潜在的爆炸与有毒气体
They do safety checks for explosives and toxic gases
然后协助机组人员撤离
helped the crew exit the Orbiter
最后再把整架飞机拖进处理厂
and eventually they tow it to the Orbiter Processing Facility
然后就在这个2700平方米的大机库里
Once inside the 2700 square meter or 29000 square foot hangar
进行约125天的检修工作
the shuttle would be processed for approximately 125 days
会有超过115个多层平台参与工作
More than 115 multi-level platforms would surround the vehicle
让工程师们得以检查其600万个部件
so engineers could check six million parts
六百万！
Six million parts!
搞没搞错？
What?
但在此之前，还要先由技术人员穿着防护服去清理机身
But first technicians would don hazmat suits to clean the vehicle
去掉一切残余的有毒或自燃物质
of any remaining toxic and hypergolic elements
拆除轨道机动系统
Then they would remove the Orbital Maneuvering System pods
以及前向机动系统组件
and the Forward Reaction Control Systems modules
方便检修及测试
to be repaired and retested
然后3个RS-25主发也得拆掉
Then crews would take off all three of the Space Shuttle's main engines, or RS-25's
其实就算放到今天，这玩意也是相当厉害的
These babies are still incredible engines
可以说是有史以来最高效的型号了
some of the most efficient engines ever made
但是每次发射之间都要进行巨额维护
But they required a healthy amount of inspection and refurbishment between each flight
有五万个零件
Each engine had 50000 parts
其中约七千个还很容易坏，需要频繁换新
and about 7000 of which were life-limited and occasionally had to be replaced
到2002年的时候，肯尼迪航天中心接手了发动机的组装工作
In 2002, Kennedy Space Center took over assembly tasks of the engines
终于不用为了翻新而运来运去了！
instead of sending them out for refurbishment
但这还不是最要命的工作
But perhaps the biggest and most daunting task of the Space Shuttle
检修那几万块吹弹可破的隔热瓦才真是要命
was inspecting the thousands and thousands of fragile silica tiles on the bottom of the Orbiter
前面已经说过，一架航天飞机根据型号的不同
There were between 24177 and 31088 tiles
会有24177到31088片绝热瓦
depending on the Orbiter
关键每一片长得还都不一样！
Every single one was unique
所以必须逐个的仔细检查与置换
and had to be carefully inspected and if damaged, replaced
还有电子仪器、货仓
And of course, all the avionics, the payload bay
液压操纵面、等等等等
the hydraulic control surfaces et cetera, et cetera
这么多东西都需要在每次飞行后被仔细检修
were carefully checked out between each flight as well
这一系列算下来，每飞一次就得需要大概650000工时的检修
In total, the Space Shuttle required no less than 650000 hours of labor between each flight
按普通人工资每小时25美刀
Say the average person made $25 an hour
那这样算下来
which I'm sure is kind of conservative
每次翻新光薪水就得付一千六百万！
for a highly trained technician
更别说这个价格其实非常保守
the cost of human labor to get a Space Shuttle ready for launch
因为大家都是高级技工
would be around 16 million dollars!
薪水当然也在平均水平之上
And again, that's being fairly conservative
不过早期情况也没这么遭
But it wasn't always this way
因为一直到1986年，挑战者号事故之后
Actually, before the Challenger accident in 1986
航天飞机才开始被要求做严格的检修与翻新
the shuttle went through much less refurbishment and checks
所以在那之前的话，问题也没严重到这个地步
So few in fact, it may have seen as little
大概只需要相当于后来1%的工时就能完成了
as almost 1% the amount of labor hours between flights
为了最大限度地避免挑战者号事故
But after the Challenger accident
NASA采用了更彻底的翻新步骤
NASA changed the entire process of getting the Space Shuttle flight ready
检查变得十分复杂与精细，覆盖了从头到尾的每个角落
and wound up going over every single inch with a fine-tooth comb
不过毕竟人命攸关的事，还是小心驶得万年船
That's probably a good thing when you're dealing with human life
再往后，到了1989年
Oh and lastly, after 1989, to get the shuttle ready
NASA有了个叫OTS的76轮运输车
it was placed on top of the Orbiter Transfer System
用来把航天飞机从轨道器处理厂
a 76 wheel transporter, to take it from the OPF
运到装配建筑
to the Vehicle Assembly building
并在这里安装巨大的外置油箱
to be mated with the external tank
以及两枚固体助推器
and the Solid Rocket Boosters
不过呢，现在这个76轮大卡车已经属于太空叉了
Fun fact, SpaceX now owns the Orbiter Transfer System to transport their boosters!
那么，我们的主角
Okay, now time for the big question
猎鹰九号又要经过怎样的检修才能再次发射呢
What does it take to get a Falcon 9 booster back to the launch pad?
答案是，我不知道
Let me start off by saying a lot of this is speculation
因为具体细节目前都还是保密的
since SpaceX doesn't make public exactly what goes into preparation
不过我们可以靠他们动作
but let's give a rundown on what they have done
以及置换的零件来做一些猜测
and what things they will be doing
首先，如果是在水面上回收
So first off, if it landed on the drone ship
会有一个小型机器人出动
a little robot actually comes out
立即固定住助推器
and grabs onto the booster and hangs on to it
免得……
so this doesn't happen
然后运输回来，大约只需要10位工作人员和两艘船
It's then transported back by a support crew of around 10 and two ships
如果是在地面上回收
But if the booster lands on land
就会有吊车把推进器放上运输车直接带走
the booster is picked up by a crane and put onto their transporter
最初的几年里
For the first few years of the Falcon 9 reuse
回收来的火箭会被运往加州豪松市翻新
the booster were shipped back to Hawthorne for the refurbishment
不过现在太空叉也有在卡纳维拉尔角建新的助推器翻新厂
But SpaceX is building a booster refurbishment facility at the cape
第一次成功回收助推器
The first booster to ever land
是在2015年12月21日的OG2任务
on December 21, 2015 for the OG2 mission
那枚火箭后来被彻底拆开研究
was extensively torn down and inspected
毕竟这还是太空叉第一次见到完整的火箭回来
Since this was the first booster that SpaceX actually caught in one piece
当然要好好检查一下
they had to check their work
看看是不是真的有完好地回收
and see if it actually came out okay
最初的13枚，或者说非Block 5火箭
On the first 13 reused boosters, or non-Block 5 boosters
我们能明显看出更换的有喷嘴后面的隔热盾与隔热毯
we know SpaceX changed out the heat shields and blankets behind the exhaust nozzles
有极其炙热的任务中烧毁的柵格翼
We know they had to fix and repair the grid fins on the extra hot missions
我们也能看出他们也花了大量的时间检修
We know they had to do a lot of inspections on the vehicle
更进一步他们还用X射线检查助推器
but they also had to run an X-ray along the booster
以保证箭身状态良好尚可用
to ensure the fuselage is still good to go
所以让我猜的话
Now I've heard speculations
彻底翻修一下Block 3/4的一级
of between 1000 to 10000 human hours of labor
大概会需要1000到10000工时
for the turnaround of the Block 3 and Block 4 boosters
但就算往大了说
And say this is terribly conservative
假设需要100000工时才能搞定
Say it's actually 100000 hours of labor
那也还不到航天飞机轨道器的1/6啊
that'd still be over six times less labor than the Space Shuttle Orbiter
猎鹰九号从零件数量上就有相当优势
The Falcon 9 has much less systems to check over than the Orbiter
所以我应该可以确信猎鹰九号的翻新工程
so I think it's pretty safe to assume there's a lot less labor hours required
远比航天飞机来的轻快
to prepare it for reflight
到了Block 5这代
We know SpaceX has a goal with their new Block 5 Falcon 9
太空叉的目标改为24至48小时内重新发射
to see it land and refly within 24 to 48 hours
每次飞行后只做保险性的检查
with nothing but inspections and checks between flights
不做任何实际的维修与换新
The overall goal of their new Block 5 booster is to be reflown 10 times
就至少成功进行10次发射
without any actual refurbishment, only inspections
Block 5型是在先前的24个成功回收的基础上设计的
They built Block 5 having learned the lessons from the 24 recoveries leading up to Block 5
如果你对更新历史有兴趣的话
if you need a reminder of what's new with Block 5
我也有个视频说了相关内容
I have a video all about
Block 5火箭及其改进之处
what Block 5 is and what has changed
初步罗列一下Block 5的更新
A quick list of things that are new with the Block 5
覆盖全箭身的隔热层
is a thermal protective coating on the whole booster
发动机旁边的液冷隔热板
a liquid cooled heat shield by the engines
然后新式的Octaweb布局，这一项大概提升了8%的推力
a bolted Octaweb, 8% increase in thrust on the first stage
还有升级的着陆腿，钛金柵格翼
upgraded retractable landing legs, titanium grid fins
升级的复合材料容器2.0以及其他大量的改进
an upgraded COPV 2.0 and a ton of tweaks
这就让火箭更加可复用了
that allow it to be even more reusable
这同时也是获得载人许可的一部分
and most importantly, rated for human flight
所以为啥猎鹰九号就不用每次做大修？
So how can the Falcon 9 booster actually be reflown without refurbishment?
不用从里到外换个遍？
Can it?
到底是有多大的不同？
What's so different about the Falcon 9 compared to the Space Shuttle?
我们先来跟固体助推器（SRB）比较一下
Well let's first compare it to the SRBs
找找差距到底在哪里
and see what it actually does differently
首先，让SRB直接掉进大海
First off, the SRBs splashed down in salt water
你觉得很省事吗
That's not really a good thing
SRB大体上就是一个
Solid Rocket Boosters are also basically giant empty canisters
塞满了橡胶质地推进剂的容器
that are loaded up with a rubber like solid propellant
每次飞行前重新填满
between each flight
但液体燃料火箭发动机的话
This is different than a liquid fueled rocket engine
就不是这么简单的东西
that has say tens of thousands of parts
一个有成千上万个零件的玩意掉进海里
If a liquid engine were to be submerged in salt water
啥结果不用我说了吧
I don't think that'd be a good thing
所以，降落在陆地或者船上
So right there is probably the biggest thing
这可能就是最重要的一点了
having a booster land on dry land or a dry ship deck is a huge leg up
至少对复用性和翻新工程来说是这样
as far as reusability and refurbishment goes
事实上
As a matter of fact
与其把SRB拖回厂
the SRBs were so expensive to refurbish
拆开来从头到尾翻新一遍
in the long run, it was more expensive to bring them back tear them down and all that
还不如直接造个新的呢
than it was just to build new ones
再回来看看轨道器
So why is the Falcon 9 booster more reusable than the Orbiter?
首先一个关键性的问题
Well first off, the Orbiter was not only a rocket
轨道器是个7人太空船，而猎鹰九号只是个运载火箭
it was also a spaceship that carried up to seven people
这就让驾驶舱、太空船内部、货舱之类的
So a lot of work and check outs went into the cockpit
都需要大量的检查与修理
the interior, the payload bay et cetera, et cetera
更别说那组火箭发动机了
let alone the actual rocket engine portion of the Orbiter
虽然RS-25至今为止都是相当先进的玩意
The RS-25 engine, although amazing
而且到后期也不再需要运到其他地方去维护
and eventually refurbished on-site
但还是需要非常可怕的工作量
still required an awful lot of work to fly again
而太空叉的梅林1D发动机
The Merlin 1D engine that SpaceX has developed
已经点火超过5600次了
has been fired over 5600 times
从设计出发点就有相当的不同
and is designed to be reflown and reused over and over with minimal inspections
虽然目前还没公布资料说到底需要多少的检修工作
How much, we don't really know yet
不过待会儿再讨论这个问题
but more on that in a second
但猎鹰九号和航天飞机最大的不同
But perhaps the biggest difference between the Falcon 9 booster and the Space Shuttle Orbiter
是再入速度
is the velocity in which each one reenters
我们对比下SRB、猎鹰九号一级和轨道器的速度
Let's compare the velocities of the SRB, the Falcon 9 first stage and the Orbiter
来让我们理解为什么它们有各自的再入系统
to help understand why each one uses their given reentry system
SRB速度上限也就4800km/h
The SRB never exceeds 4800 kilometers an hour
而且也不会离开大气层
and it also stays lower in the atmosphere
因此也不需要为再入减速
so it doesn't require any kind of slow down before it reenters
没出过大气何来“再”入？
well because it never really exited in the first place
而对于猎鹰九号
The Falcon 9 on the other hand
它最快能达到8000km/h
goes from up to about 8000 kilometers an hour
最慢也有5000km/h
down to as low as about 5000 kilometers an hour
用反推进技术帮助减速
in order to survive reentry using its retropropulsion
不出意外的话
But it's safe to say it will probably never see
以后的最高速度应该也不会超出8000km/h太多
much more than 8000 kilometers an hour
轨道器的再入就快得多了，速度有27000km/h
The Orbiter reenters at speeds of up to 27000 kilometers an hour
但是它会在在上层稀薄大气中
but it slowly bleeds off a lot of its speed
慢慢降低速度
in the upper atmosphere
你看
Wow
速度上的差距是非常大的
Those are some pretty big differences in velocity
因为猎鹰九号再入速度只有不超过8000km/h
Since the Falcon 9 booster reenters at only 8000 kilometers an hour
它经受的热量就只有轨道器的大概1/40
it experiences up to almost 40 times less heat compared to the Orbiter
很奇怪对不对！
What? How can that be?
我来计算一下给你们看看
Well, since the first stage of the Falcon 9
8000+km/h这个速度最多最多也不过轨道器的1/3
only gets up to at most about a third of orbital velocity
这一点就让其产生的热量远小于轨道器的1/3
it receives much less than just 1/3rd of the amount of heat
运动物体迎风面产生的热量
The compressed gas on the leading edge of any vehicle
与速度是平方关系
will see heat increase by velocity squared
但是传输到火箭上的热量就还要再乘个速度
but the thermal energy transferred to the rocket
也就是3次方
goes as velocity cubed!
所以如果什么东西运动速度变成了四倍
So that means if a vehicle is traveling four times faster
那这货前部就会烫64倍！
the bow wave in front can get 64 times hotter!
因为速度是4倍，再*4，就是平方
'Cause that's four times faster, times four, so squared
再再*4，就是立方，得到64倍
times another four, cubed, so 64!
虽然可能说的太简单了点
Now this is an oversimplification
不过这也是为啥航天飞机会需要前缘的碳-碳绝热材料
but that's why the Space Shuttle needed those carbon-carbon leading edges
以及底部大量硅瓦
and those silica tiles all over the bottom of it to survive reentry
而且不管速度慢得多
Not only that, but the Falcon 9
猎鹰九号还有一个再入点火的机制
also does an a pretty significant retropropulsion burn
会进一步地减少火箭受到的热量
before it reenters, to ensure the vehicle can survive
航天飞机没有这样的机制
The Space Shuttle didn't do any of this
因为它的底面很大
because it relied on its large surface area
在稀薄大气中呆几分钟的时间也能减少不少速度
to slowly bleed the speed off for several minutes
事实上
As a matter of fact
航天飞机要花掉接近10倍的时间
the Space Shuttle spent almost 10 times the amount of time
来散发掉再入时产生的热量
radiating heat off through reentry
这差不多也是其隔热盾的工作原理
which is the key to how its non-ablative heat shield worked
总的来说
So long story short
猎鹰九号首先再入速度很慢，不会产生太多热量
The first stage is going slow enough to not get crazy hot
所以需要的绝热系统也很少
so it doesn't require nearly as much thermal protection
应该可以说
Therefore it's probably safe to say
只要不出岔子，这能避免大量翻新工作
it doesn't require as much refurbishment, hopefully
最后再来说说我的想法
So some final thoughts on all this
首先，为什么我觉得猎鹰九号不会走
First off, the reason why I think the Falcon 9 will actually achieve reusability
航天飞机彻底失败的老路
when the Space Shuttle couldn't
其实首要的是工程理念差异
is mostly due to the engineering philosophy of SpaceX
太空叉的火箭是长期进化的
They are constantly tweaking their rocket
用其生产副总的话说
to the point where according to SpaceX's VP of production, Andy Lambert
“太空叉从未制造‘两个完全相同的火箭’”
SpaceX has "Never built any two vehicles identically
“这就是太空叉的创新之处”
"such is the pace of innovation at SpaceX."
而航天飞机就完全不是一回事了
Now this is quite different from the Space Shuttle
总共也就5个能飞的
that had only only five operational vehicles
30年间基本上就没怎么更新过
that changed very little in their 30 years of operation
虽然航天飞机的第一版
As a matter of fact, phase one of the Space Shuttle
再更新前也只飞了四次
was only the first four flights of Columbia
但再之后的改进就几乎没有了
After that, further development would be minimal
而猎鹰九号，如果什么设计没达到预期
But with the Falcon 9, if an idea doesn't work out
太空叉完全可以在建造下一枚火箭的时候
they can literally make that change
就做出修改
on one of the next manufactured boosters
如果是需要较大变动的话
And if it's a really big change
就放在下一Block实现
they'll do that on the next Block iteration
真要说的话，航天飞机也不是完全没改进过
The Space Shuttle's design didn't exactly freeze
但其30年间那点进化
but it certainly didn't evolve nearly as much in 30 years
实在是比猎鹰九号这8年来少太多了
as the Falcon 9 has in eight years
虽然这8年里有些设计也显得莫名其妙
Some might consider this much change reckless
但考虑到其最终目的
but considering the end goal
是设计制造真正稳定可复用的火箭
is to actually have a reusable vehicle
这样一个激进的策略我真的觉得很棒
I'm really glad they're pushing this aggressively
我也完全不想再去等个30年
I just can't wait another 30 years
最后，如果有人说
And lastly to those that think SpaceX
太空叉永远没法把复用成本降到能回本的程度
won't be able to make it worth the cost of reflying
或者质疑这样是不是真的有什么意义
or who question whether or not it'll be worth it for them
这又关我们啥事呢
luckily for us, it really doesn't matter
太空叉是个私企
SpaceX is a private company
影响他们抉择的主要因素当然就是能不能赚到钱
They will only do what makes the most financial sense
也许几年后他们会发现这确实回不了本
So if after a few years they look back and realize
造个新的还是比较省钱省事
it's more expensive to try to refly these things than it is to make a new one
那为了赚钱大不了就不干了呗
I'm sure they'll stop doing so because they don't wanna lose money
他们没有任何义务去弄出可复用的火箭
They don't owe it to anyone to reuse their rockets
完全只是觉得有戏，觉得能省钱
It's only in their best interest
觉得能让利益最大化
to figure out how to do so so they can maximize profits
这就很不同于航天飞机了
And that's just different than the Space Shuttle
后者承载着整个国家对可复用性的希望
which had the weight of the entire nation's expectations to be reusable
不管设计能不能达到预期效果
Whether or not the system put in place actually made sense
一旦弄出来
it was too late
就没有什么修改的空间了
There was no room for major changes per say
毕竟议会不懂这事，他们的耐心也很有限
since Congress would probably frown upon
“你看，这概念不行，还是别搞航天飞机了”
"Well this didn't work out, let's scrap the entire idea."
所以就我个人觉得
So personally
现在这时代，到处都注重创新，材料科学也有长足的发展
I think with this new age of innovation and materials
软硬件方面都在飞速进化
rapid evolution of hardware and software
领导也要求他们作出各种各样的尝试
and leadership that simply requires they keep trying
直到达成目标
until they figure it out
所以我觉得我们已经有一只脚
I think we're finally entering a new era
踏入可复用火箭与航天客机的大门了
of reusable and airliner like rockets
未来充满希望
Hopefully!
你们怎么想？
So what are your thoughts?
可复用是近在咫尺了
Is actual reusability finally upon us
还是认为太空叉不行人类药丸？
or do you think we're still going to be stuck in refurbishment land?
字幕翻译alprc，校对润色压制给虫，记得点赞投币分享收藏关注转发哦
如果有任何问题的话
What other questions do you have?
有什么见解、疑问、或者视频内容建议
Let me know your thoughts, questions, and video requests
请在下面留言！
in the comments below!
感谢来自kNews的Lukas提供这些动画
Thanks to Lukas from kNews for his amazing animations
我一直很喜欢他的作品
I've always been a fan of his work
也很高兴可以合作
and was so happy to work with him on some of these visuals
别忘了去看看他的频道
Be sure and check out his awesome channel
里面有很多航天新闻与视频
where he does updates on spaceflight news and other great spaceflight topics as well
精彩尽在kNews！
Check it out, kNews!
也感谢我Patreon上的赞助者们
And of course I owe a huge thanks to my Patreon supporters
让本期与每一期《每日宇航员》节目成为现实
for helping me make this and all other Everyday Astronaut content possible
你们太厉害了
You guys are seriously amazing!
是你们激励我提高致己的姿势水平
And you help me stay sane during all these long bouts of research
还有我的discord和reddit子版块的朋友们帮我写脚本做研究
They hang out in my exclusive discord and our exclusive subreddit to help me script and research
如果你想帮忙
If you wanna help contribute
记得去patreon链接给我资瓷一下
please visit patreon.com/everydayastronaut
非常感谢
Thank you, seriously thank you
和往常一样，本期音乐全原创
As always, all the music in my videos is original
可以去下方链接免费下载
Feel free to check it out for free at soundcloud.com/everydayastronaut
记得分享给朋友哦
Tell a friend
我这件衣服也可以去我的网店了解一哈
Hey guess what? This ridiculous shirt is finally available in my web store
还有各种其他东西比如帽子杯子
along with a lot of other fun things like hats, mugs
火箭模型之类的
prints of rocket launches or original other work
还有各种好玩的
and lots of other fun stuff
链接见下
at everydayastronaut.com/shop
祝你笑口常开
Have fun
再次感谢各位
Thanks everybody, that does it for me
我是Tim Dodd，来自《每日宇航员》频道
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut
把航天带入寻常百姓家！
bringing space down to Earth for everyday people